<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A wife novv the widdow of Sir Thomas Overburye Being a most exquisite and singular poem of the choice of a wife. Whereunto are added many witty characters, and conceited newes, written by himselfe and other learned gentlemen his friends.</title>
            <title>Wife now a widowe</title>
            <author>Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120266</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20960</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08592)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20960)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1110:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A wife novv the widdow of Sir Thomas Overburye Being a most exquisite and singular poem of the choice of a wife. Whereunto are added many witty characters, and conceited newes, written by himselfe and other learned gentlemen his friends.</title>
                  <title>Wife now a widowe</title>
                  <author>Overbury, Thomas, Sir, 1581-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Griffin] for Lawrence Lisle, and are to bee sold at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Tigers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Characters and characteristics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A WIFE NOVV <hi>The Widdow</hi> OF SIR THOMAS OVERBVRYE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Being</hi> A moſt exquiſite and ſingular Poem <hi>of the choice of a Wife.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHEREVNTO ARE ADDED</hi> many witty Characters, and conceited <hi>Newes, written by himſelfe and other</hi> learned Gentlemen his friends.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dignum laude virum muſa vetat mori,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Coelo muſa beat.</hi>
                     </l> 
                     <bibl>Hor: car: lib. 3.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Lawrence Liſle,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Paules Church-yard,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Tigers head.</hi> 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:2"/>
                  <head>THE PRINTER TO the Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HY ignorance may challenge libertie enough, not to reliſh the deepe Arte of Poetry: becauſe opinion makes thee obſtinate; and rude tradition hath taught thee nothing but an abuſe of knowledge. For when thou rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest a quaffing fellowes barbariſme, a worthy-written ſtile in Tragedies, and a colluſiue flouriſh onely fronted with the name of excellent; thou ouer-lookſt them all with the vſuall contempt or aſperſion of friuolous, and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticke labours, putting no difference betwixt the horſe pictured on a ſigne-post, and the curious limbd <hi>Pegaſus:</hi> But the age giues one comfort in extremitie, that as there is a <hi>Lizard</hi> which aſſailes; ſo is there one, which wonders at the maieſtie of man: ſure I am if any ſhall neglect, nay not commend the worth of this ſo generally approued Poem; he may (if it proceeds from nice critiſciſme) bee well excluded as a churliſh retainer to the Muſes; (if
<pb facs="tcp:20960:3"/>
from a direct plaine dealing) he must be degraded for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiencie. For had ſuch a volume been extant among the ancient Romanes, though they wanted our eaſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations of wit, by printing; yet would they rather, and more eaſily, haue committed the ſenſe hereof to braſſe, and cedar leaues, then let ſuch an Author, baue loſt his due eternitie. If to converſe with a creature ſo amiable, heere deſcribed, be thought more then difficult, let then the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of it be admirable, which hath expreſſed the ſoule in ſo compact aforme of body. The ſurpluſage, that now exceeds the last edition, was (that I may bee honestly impartiall) in ſome things only to be challenged by the first author, but others now added, (little inferior to the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due) being in nature anſwerable, and first tranſcrib'd by Gentlemen of the ſame qualitie, I haue vpon good induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, made publike with warrantie of their and my owne credit. Not doubting therefore to be doubly diſcharged, both by the verdict of conſcience and the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerued thankes of all iudicious Readers, I bid you euery one farewell, May 16. 1614.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:3"/>
                  <head>A MORNING-SACRIFICE to the Author.</head>
                  <l>THe only curſe or bleſſing that betides</l>
                  <l>To men, (made doubtful) by their beauteous brides,</l>
                  <l>Could neuer (being apparent) ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>The full enioyer, with ſatietie</l>
                  <l>Of confidence, to call them good, or bad,</l>
                  <l>So much; as this good worke (which chiefly had</l>
                  <l>A faire creation, to create anew</l>
                  <l>The ſoule of ſome, and to confirme ſome few)</l>
                  <l>Hath reſcued ſhameleſſe iudgment from the ſuit</l>
                  <l>Of meere opinion, and ſpeakes abſolute.</l>
                  <l>This widdow booke then, wife to rauiſh'd skill,</l>
                  <l>Married and made by the moſt maiden quill</l>
                  <l>Of one, not loſt to her, though ſhe to him,</l>
                  <l>Hath leaue to liue thus ſingle; richly trim,</l>
                  <l>Yet neuer to be challeng'd; being ſo chaſte</l>
                  <l>In puritie, and not to be imbrac't</l>
                  <l>Without the reuerence of hir wedlocks loue;</l>
                  <l>Which when thou ſeem'ſt vnwilling to approue,</l>
                  <l>Scorne a compleat faire woman; and ſo grudge</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thou haſt no libertie to iudge.</l>
                  <l>Nor, let thy glorious confidence preſume,</l>
                  <l>To make this Lady plyant, through perfume</l>
                  <l>Oſpowdred phraſe, and robes, or complement;</l>
                  <l>For though on pilgrimage thy learning went</l>
                  <l>In queſt of ſuch a wonder, yet thy paines</l>
                  <l>Were loſt, although thy labri'ng ſuit obtaines:</l>
                  <l>For woman (in the abſtract) hath no more</l>
                  <l>Then hath the wife, the widdow, maiden, whore,</l>
                  <l>And altogether; therefore thou haſt none,</l>
                  <l>Except thy labours purchaſe ſuch a one:</l>
                  <l>Which (to haue ſaid) they all agreed in Eue</l>
                  <l>Is all enough; if iealous man beleene.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>By <hi>I. S. Lincolnienſis</hi> Gentleman.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="encomia">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:4"/>
                  <head>Briefe Panegyrickes to the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors praiſe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <head>To the Booke.</head>
                     <l>EXpoſ'd to all thou wilt leſſe worthy ſeeme</l>
                     <l>I feare: wiues common, all men diſeſteeme;</l>
                     <l>Yet ſome things haue a differing fate: ſome fret</l>
                     <l>We doubt in wares which are in corners ſet:</l>
                     <l>Hid medalls ruſt, which being vſd grow bright;</l>
                     <l>The day more friendeth vertue then the night</l>
                     <l>Thou though more common, then maiſt ſeeme more good</l>
                     <l>I onely wiſh thou mayſt be vnderſtood.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. R.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <l>TO make a Wife of wit, or meere Philoſophie,</l>
                     <l>And deck her vp with flowers of ſweeteſt poeſie,</l>
                     <l>Is no hard taske, but ſuch a one of fleſh to find</l>
                     <l>Would weary all the wits and bodies of mankind<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Since worſe muſt ſerue the turne, then men muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</l>
                     <l>To take ſuch as they find, not ſuch as they invent.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>T. B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="encomium">
                     <l>WEll hast thou ſaid that woman ſhould be ſuch;</l>
                     <l>And were they that, had but a third as much</l>
                     <l>I would be maried too: but that I know</l>
                     <l>Not what ſhee is, but ſhould be thou dost ſhow:</l>
                     <l>So let me praiſe thy worke, and let my life</l>
                     <l>Be ſingle, or thy widow be my wife.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>X. Z.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:4"/>
                  <head>Of the choice of a Wife.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>IF I were to chuſe a woman,</l>
                     <l>As who knowes but I may marry,</l>
                     <l>I would trust the eye of no man</l>
                     <l>Nor a tongue that may miſcarry:</l>
                     <l>For in way of loue and glory</l>
                     <l>Each tongue best tells his own ſtorie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>First to make my choice the bolder</l>
                     <l>I would haue her child to ſuch</l>
                     <l>Whoſe free vertuous liues are older</l>
                     <l>Then antiquitie can touch,</l>
                     <l>For tis ſeldom ſeen that bloud</l>
                     <l>Giues a beauty great and good.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet an ancient ſtocke may bring</l>
                     <l>Branches I confeſſe of worth,</l>
                     <l>Like rich mantles ſhadowing</l>
                     <l>Thoſe deſcents that brought them forth,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſuch hills though gilded ſhow</l>
                     <l>Soonest feele the age of ſnow.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Therefore to preuent ſuch care</l>
                     <l>That repentance ſoone may bring,</l>
                     <l>Like Merchants I would chuſe my ware,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vſe-full good,</hi> not glittering.</l>
                     <l>He that weds for ſtate or face</l>
                     <l>Buyes a horſe to looſe a race.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet I would haue her faire as any,</l>
                     <l>But her owne not kiſt away:</l>
                     <l>I would haue her free to many</l>
                     <l>Looke on all like equall day,</l>
                     <l>But deſcending to the Sea</l>
                     <l>Make her ſet with none but me.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If ſhe be not tall tis better,</l>
                     <l>For that word, <hi>A goodly woman,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:20960:5"/>
Prints it ſelfe in ſuch a letter</l>
                     <l>That it leaues vnſtudied no man;</l>
                     <l>I would haue my miſtreſſe grow</l>
                     <l>Only tall to anſwer no.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yet I would not haue her looſe</l>
                     <l>So much breeding as to fling</l>
                     <l>Vnbecomming ſcorne on thoſe</l>
                     <l>That must worſhip euery thing.</l>
                     <l>Let her feare looſe lookes to ſcatter,</l>
                     <l>And looſe men will feare to flatter.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Children I would haue her beare</l>
                     <l>More for loue of name then bed,</l>
                     <l>So each child I haue is heire</l>
                     <l>To another maidenhead;</l>
                     <l>For ſhee that in the act's afraid</l>
                     <l>Euery night's another maide.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such a one as when ſhee's wood</l>
                     <l>Bluſhes not for ill thoughts past,</l>
                     <l>But ſo innocently good</l>
                     <l>That her dreames are euer chaſte;</l>
                     <l>For that maide that thinks a ſin</l>
                     <l>Has betrai'd the fort ſhee's in.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In my viſitation ſtill</l>
                     <l>I would haue her ſeatter feares,</l>
                     <l>How this man, and that was ill;</l>
                     <l>After proteſtations teares;</l>
                     <l>And who vowes a conſtant life</l>
                     <l>Crownes a meritorious wife.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>When the Priest firſt giues our hands,</l>
                     <l>I would haue her thinke but thus:</l>
                     <l>In what high and holy bands</l>
                     <l>Heauen, like twins, hath planted vs,</l>
                     <l>That like Aarons rod together</l>
                     <l>Both may bud, grow green, and wither.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:5"/>
                  <argument>
                     <head>THE METHOD.</head>
                     <p>FIrst of Mariage, and the effect thereof, children. Then of his contrarie, <hi>Luſt;</hi> then for his choice. First, his opinion negatiuely, what ſhould not be: the first cauſes in it, that is, neither <hi>Beauty, Birth,</hi> nor <hi>Portion.</hi> Then affirmatiuely, what ſhould bee, of which kind there are fower: <hi>Goodneſſe, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Diſcretion,</hi> and as a ſecond thing <hi>Beauty.</hi> The first onely is abſolutely good, the other being built vpon the first doe likewiſe become ſo. Then the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of that woman by loue to himſelfe, which makes her a wife. And lastly the only condition of a wife, <hi>Fitneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <head>A Wife.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ach Woman is a <hi>briefe</hi> of Woman-kind,</l>
                     <l>And doth in little euen as much containe;</l>
                     <l>As, in one Day &amp; Night, all life we find,</l>
                     <l>Of either, More, is but the ſame againe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God</hi> fram'd Her ſo, that to Her <hi>husband,</hi> She,</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Eue,</hi> ſhould all the <hi>world of Women</hi> be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:6"/>
                     <l>So fram'd he <hi>Both,</hi> that <hi>neither</hi> power he gaue,</l>
                     <l>Vſe of themſelues, but by <hi>exchange,</hi> to make:</l>
                     <l>Whence in their Face the <hi>Fayre</hi> no pleaſure haue,</l>
                     <l>But by <hi>refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xe</hi> of what thence <hi>other</hi> take:</l>
                     <l>Our Lips in their owne Kiſſe no pleaſure find,</l>
                     <l>Toward their proper Face, our Eyes are blind.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So God in <hi>Eue</hi> did <hi>perfit</hi> Man, <hi>begun,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till then, in vaine much of himſelfe he had,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Adam</hi> God created onely <hi>one,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eue,</hi> and the <hi>world to come</hi> in <hi>Eue</hi> he made;</l>
                     <l>We are <hi>two halfes,</hi> whiles each from other ſtraies,</l>
                     <l>Both barren are; <hi>Ioyn'd both</hi> their <hi>like</hi> can raiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>At firſt <hi>both Sexes</hi> were in <hi>Man</hi> combin'de,</l>
                     <l>Man, a <hi>Shee-man</hi> did in his body breed;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> was <hi>Eues, Eue</hi> mother of Mankinde,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eue</hi> from <hi>Liue-fleſh,</hi> Man did from <hi>Dust</hi> proceed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>One</hi> thus made <hi>two, Mariage</hi> doth revnite,</l>
                     <l>And makes them both but <hi>one Hermaphrodite.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Man</hi> did but the <hi>well-being</hi> of his life</l>
                     <l>From <hi>woman</hi> take, her <hi>Being</hi> ſhe from <hi>Man,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And therefore <hi>Eue</hi> created was a Wife,</l>
                     <l>And at the end of all, her <hi>Sex</hi> began:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mariage</hi> their obiect is; their <hi>Being</hi> then,</l>
                     <l>And now <hi>Perfection,</hi> they receiue from <hi>Men.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:6"/>
                     <l>Mariage, to all, whoſe ioyes <hi>two parties</hi> be,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>doubled</hi> are by boing <hi>parted</hi> ſo,</l>
                     <l>Wherein the very <hi>act</hi> is chaſtitie,</l>
                     <l>Whereby <hi>two Soules</hi> into <hi>one Body</hi> goe,</l>
                     <l>It makes <hi>two one,</hi> whiles heere they liuing be,</l>
                     <l>And after death in their <hi>Poſteritie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God</hi> to <hi>each Man a priuate woman</hi> gaue,</l>
                     <l>That in that <hi>Center</hi> his <hi>deſires</hi> might ſtint,</l>
                     <l>That he a <hi>comfort like himſelfe</hi> might haue,</l>
                     <l>And that on her <hi>his like</hi> he might <hi>imprint.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Double</hi> is Womans <hi>vſe,</hi> part of their end</l>
                     <l>Doth on <hi>this Age,</hi> part on the <hi>next</hi> depend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We are but <hi>part of Time,</hi> yet cannot die,</l>
                     <l>Till we the world a <hi>freſh ſupply</hi> haue lent,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Children</hi> are Bodies ſole <hi>Eternitie;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nature</hi> is <hi>Gods, Art</hi> is <hi>Mans</hi> inſtrument.</l>
                     <l>Now all <hi>Mans Art</hi> but only dead things makes,</l>
                     <l>But here in <hi>Man</hi> in things of <hi>life</hi> partakes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For wandring <hi>Luſt;</hi> I know tis infinite,</l>
                     <l>It ſtill <hi>begins,</hi> and addes not more to more,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>guilt</hi> is euerlaſting, the <hi>delight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This</hi> inſtant doth not feele of <hi>that</hi> before.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>taſte</hi> of it is only in the <hi>Senſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>operation,</hi> in the <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:7"/>
                     <l>Woman is not <hi>Luſts bounds,</hi> but <hi>Woman-kind.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>One</hi> is <hi>Loues number,</hi> who from that doth fall,</l>
                     <l>Hath loſt his hold, and no <hi>new rost</hi> ſhall find,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vice</hi> hath no meane, but not to be at all;</l>
                     <l>A <hi>wife</hi> is that <hi>Enough, Lust</hi> cannot find,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Lust</hi> is ſtill with <hi>want,</hi> or <hi>too-much pinde.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Bate <hi>Lust</hi> the Sin, my ſhare is eu'n with his,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Not to Lust,</hi> and <hi>to Enioy</hi> is one:</l>
                     <l>And More or Leſſe paſt, <hi>equall</hi> Nothing is,</l>
                     <l>I ſtill haue <hi>one,</hi> Luſt <hi>one at once</hi> alone:</l>
                     <l>And though the woman often changed be,</l>
                     <l>Yet Hee's the ſame without varietie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mariage</hi> our <hi>Luſt</hi> (as twere with fuell fire)</l>
                     <l>Doth, with a medicine <hi>of the ſame,</hi> allay;</l>
                     <l>And not <hi>forbid,</hi> but <hi>rectifie deſire.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My ſelfe</hi> I cannot chuſe, <hi>my wife</hi> I may:</l>
                     <l>And, in the choice of <hi>Her,</hi> it much doth lye,</l>
                     <l>To mend my ſelfe in my Poſteritie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O rather let me <hi>Loue,</hi> then <hi>be in Loue,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So let me chuſe as <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>Friend</hi> to find.</l>
                     <l>Let me forget hir <hi>Sex</hi> when I <hi>approue.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beaſts</hi> likeneſſe lyes in <hi>ſhape,</hi> but <hi>ours</hi> in <hi>minde:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our <hi>ſoules no Sexes</hi> haue, their Loue is cleane,</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Sex,</hi> both in the <hi>better part</hi> are <hi>Men.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:7"/>
                     <l>But Phiſicke for our <hi>luſt</hi> their <hi>Bodies</hi> be,</l>
                     <l>But matter fit to ſhew our <hi>Loue</hi> vpon,</l>
                     <l>But onely <hi>Shells</hi> for our <hi>poſteritie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their ſoules were giu'n leſt man ſhould be alone;</l>
                     <l>For, but the <hi>Soules interpreters, words be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Without which <hi>Bodies</hi> are no Companie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>That <hi>goodly frame</hi> we ſee of Fleſh and bloud,</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Faſhion</hi> is, not <hi>weight,</hi> it is I ſay</l>
                     <l>But their <hi>Laye-part,</hi> but well digeſted food;</l>
                     <l>Tis but twixt <hi>Dust, and Duſt, Life's middle way:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The worth of it is nothing that is <hi>ſeene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But only that it holds a <hi>Soule</hi> within.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And all the carnall <hi>Beauty</hi> of my wife,</l>
                     <l>Is but skin-deep, but to <hi>two Senſes</hi> knowne;</l>
                     <l>Short euen of Pictures, ſhorter liu'd then Life,</l>
                     <l>And yet the <hi>loue</hi> ſuruiues that's built thereon<hi>:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For our <hi>Imagination</hi> is too high,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Bodies</hi> when they meet to ſatisfie.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All Shapes, all Colours are <hi>alike</hi> in <hi>Night,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor doth our <hi>Touch</hi> diſtinguiſh <hi>foule or faire:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But Mans <hi>imagination,</hi> and his <hi>ſight;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thoſe, but the firſt weeke, by Cuſtome are</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Both</hi> made alike, which diffred at <hi>first view;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor can that diffrence, <hi>Abſence</hi> much renew.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:8"/>
                     <l>Nor can that <hi>Beauty</hi> lying in the <hi>Face,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But meerely by <hi>imagination</hi> be</l>
                     <l>Enioy'd by vs in an <hi>inferior place.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor can that <hi>Beauty</hi> by <hi>enioying</hi> we</l>
                     <l>Make <hi>ours become,</hi> ſo our <hi>deſire</hi> growes tame:</l>
                     <l>We changed are, but it remaines the ſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Birth,</hi> leſſe then <hi>beauty,</hi> ſhall my <hi>reaſon</hi> blinde,</l>
                     <l>Hir <hi>birth</hi> goes to my <hi>Children,</hi> not to me.</l>
                     <l>Rather had I that <hi>actiue gentry</hi> finde,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vertue,</hi> then <hi>paſsiue</hi> from hir Aunceſtrie;</l>
                     <l>Rather in <hi>her aliue</hi> one vertue ſee,</l>
                     <l>Then all the reſt dead in her <hi>Pedigree.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>In the Degrees, high rather be ſhee plac't,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Nature</hi> then of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Pollicie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gentry</hi> is but a <hi>relique</hi> of Time-paſt,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Loue</hi> doth only but the <hi>preſent</hi> ſee;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Things</hi> were firſt made then <hi>words:</hi> She were the <hi>ſame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With,</hi> or <hi>without, that title</hi> or that name.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As for (the oddes of Sexes) <hi>Portion;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor will I ſhun it, nor my ayme it make.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Birth, Beauty, Weal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h,</hi> are nothing worth alone,</l>
                     <l>All theſe I would for <hi>good Additions</hi> take,</l>
                     <l>Not for <hi>Good Parts;</hi> thoſe <hi>two</hi> are ill combind,</l>
                     <l>Whom any <hi>third</hi> thing <hi>from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues</hi> hath ioynd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:8"/>
                     <l>Rather then theſe, the obiect of my <hi>Loue</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let it be <hi>Good,</hi> when theſe with vertue goe,</l>
                     <l>They (in themſelues <hi>indiffrent,)</hi> vertues proue.</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Good</hi> (like Fire) turnes all things to be ſo.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gods Image</hi> in Her <hi>Soule,</hi> ô let me place</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Loue</hi> vpon, not <hi>Adams</hi> in Her <hi>Face.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Good,</hi> is a fairer attribute then <hi>White,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tis the <hi>Mind's beauty</hi> keeps the <hi>other</hi> ſweet:</l>
                     <l>That's not ſtill one, nor mortall with the light,</l>
                     <l>Nor glaſſe, nor painting can it counterfet,</l>
                     <l>Shees truly faire, whoſe <hi>beauty</hi> is <hi>vnſeen</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like <hi>heau'n</hi> faire <hi>ſight-ward,</hi> but more faire <hi>within.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By <hi>Good,</hi> I would haue <hi>Holy</hi> vnderſtood,</l>
                     <l>So <hi>God</hi> Shee cannot loue, but alſo <hi>mee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The law requires our <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>deeds</hi> be good,</l>
                     <l>Religion euen the <hi>Thoughts</hi> doth ſanctifie:</l>
                     <l>And ſhee is <hi>more a Maide</hi> which <hi>rauiſh't</hi> is,</l>
                     <l>Then Shee which only doth but <hi>wiſh amiſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Luſt</hi> only by <hi>Religion</hi> is withſtood,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Luſts</hi> obiect is aliue, his ſtrength within,</l>
                     <l>Moralitie reſiſts but in <hi>cold bloud,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Reſpect of <hi>Credit</hi> feareth <hi>ſhame</hi> not <hi>ſin.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But no place <hi>darke enough</hi> for ſuch offence</l>
                     <l>She findes, that's <hi>watch't</hi> by her owne <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:9"/>
                     <l>Then may I <hi>trust Her Body</hi> with her <hi>Mind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, therevpon ſecure, need neuer know</l>
                     <l>The pangs of <hi>Ielouſie:</hi> and <hi>Loue</hi> doth find</l>
                     <l>More paine to <hi>doubt</hi> her falſe, then <hi>know</hi> her ſo;</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Patience</hi> is of euills that are known,</l>
                     <l>The certaine Remedie; but <hi>Doubt</hi> hath none.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And be that Thought <hi>once</hi> ſtirr'd 'twill neuer die,</l>
                     <l>Nor will the griefe more milde by Cuſtome proue;</l>
                     <l>Nor yet <hi>amendment</hi> can it ſatisfie,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>anguiſh</hi> more or leſſe is <hi>as our Loue:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This miſerie doth <hi>Ielouſie</hi> enſue,</l>
                     <l>That we may proue Her <hi>falſe,</hi> but cannot <hi>True.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Suſpition</hi> may the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>Luſt</hi> reſtraine,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Good</hi> preuents from hauing ſuch a <hi>will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Wife</hi> that's <hi>Good,</hi> doth <hi>Chaſte and more</hi> containe,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Chaſte</hi> is but an <hi>Abſtinence</hi> from ill:</l>
                     <l>And in a <hi>Wife</hi> that's <hi>Bad,</hi> although the <hi>best</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of qualities; yet in a <hi>Good</hi> the <hi>least.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To barre the meanes is <hi>Care,</hi> not <hi>Ielouſie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Some <hi>lawfull</hi> things to be auoyded are,</l>
                     <l>When, they <hi>occaſion</hi> of <hi>vnlawfull</hi> be.</l>
                     <l>Leſt ere it hurts is beſt deſcride afarre.</l>
                     <l>Luſt is a ſinne <hi>of two;</hi> he that is ſure</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>either</hi> part, may be of <hi>both</hi> ſecure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:9"/>
                     <l>Giue me next <hi>Good,</hi> an <hi>vnderſtanding Wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By Nature <hi>wiſe,</hi> not <hi>learned</hi> by much Art,</l>
                     <l>Some <hi>knowledge</hi> on Hir ſide will all my life</l>
                     <l>More ſcope of Converſation impart,</l>
                     <l>Beſides, Her inborne vertue fortifie.</l>
                     <l>They are moſt firmely good, that beſt know why.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A <hi>paſsiue vnderſtanding</hi> to conceiue,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Iudgment</hi> to diſcerne, I wiſh to find,</l>
                     <l>Beyond that, all as hazardous I leaue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>pregnant wit</hi> in Woman-kind,</l>
                     <l>What it findes malleable maketh fraile,</l>
                     <l>And doth not adde more <hi>ballaſte,</hi> but more <hi>ſaile.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bookes</hi> are a part of Mans prerogatiue,</l>
                     <l>In formall Inck they <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Voyces</hi> hold,</l>
                     <l>That we to them our ſolitude may giue,</l>
                     <l>And make <hi>Time-preſent</hi> trauaile that of <hi>old.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Life, <hi>Fame</hi> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eceth longer at the end,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Bookes</hi> it farther backward doe extend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Domeſticke</hi> Charge doth beſt that Sex befit,</l>
                     <l>Contiguous buiſnes, ſo to fixe the Mind,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Leaſure</hi> ſpace for <hi>Fancies</hi> not admit:</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Leaſure</hi> tis corrupteth <hi>Woman-kind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Elſe being plac'd from many vices free,</l>
                     <l>They had to heau'n a ſhorter cut then we.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:10"/>
                     <l>As <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>knowing,</hi> let her be <hi>Diſcreet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That to the others <hi>weight,</hi> doth <hi>Faſhion</hi> bring,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diſcretion</hi> doth conſider what is <hi>Fit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> but what is <hi>lawfull,</hi> but the <hi>Thing</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not <hi>Circumſtances; Learning</hi> is and <hi>wit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In Men but <hi>curious folly</hi> without it.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To keep their Name when 'tis in others hands</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diſcretion</hi> askes, their <hi>Credit</hi> is by farre</l>
                     <l>More <hi>fraile</hi> then <hi>They,</hi> on likelyhoods it ſtands,</l>
                     <l>And hard to be diſprou'd <hi>Lust's ſlanders</hi> are.</l>
                     <l>Their <hi>Carriage,</hi> not their <hi>Chaſtitie</hi> alone,</l>
                     <l>Muſt keep their <hi>Name</hi> chaſt from ſuſpition.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Womens <hi>Behauiour</hi> is a ſurer barre</l>
                     <l>Then is their <hi>No: That</hi> fairely doth <hi>deny</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Without <hi>denying, thereby</hi> kept they are</l>
                     <l>Safe eu'n from <hi>Hope;</hi> in part to blame is ſhee,</l>
                     <l>Which hath <hi>without conſent</hi> bin only tride;</l>
                     <l>He comes too <hi>neere,</hi> that comes <hi>to be denide.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Now ſince a <hi>Woman</hi> we to <hi>Marie</hi> are,</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> not a <hi>Soule</hi> alone;</l>
                     <l>When one is <hi>Good,</hi> then be the other <hi>Faire,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beauty</hi> is <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Beauty</hi> both in one,</l>
                     <l>Be Shee ſo faire as change can yeeld no gaine,</l>
                     <l>So faire, as Shee moſt Women elſe containe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:10"/>
                     <l>At leaſt ſo Faire let me imagine Her,</l>
                     <l>That thought to me is <hi>Truth; Opinion</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cannot in matter of <hi>opinion</hi> erre;</l>
                     <l>With no <hi>Eyes</hi> ſhall I ſee her but <hi>mine owne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And as my <hi>Fancie Her</hi> conceiues to be,</l>
                     <l>Euen ſuch my Sences both, do <hi>Feele,</hi> and <hi>See.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Face</hi> we may the ſeate of <hi>Beauty</hi> call,</l>
                     <l>In it the reliſh of the reſt doth lye,</l>
                     <l>Nay eu'n a figure of the <hi>Minde</hi> withall:</l>
                     <l>And of the <hi>Face</hi> the <hi>Life</hi> moues in the <hi>Eye;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No things elſe being <hi>two</hi> ſo like we ſee,</l>
                     <l>So like, that they <hi>two</hi> but in Number be.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beauty</hi> in <hi>decent ſhape,</hi> and <hi>Colours</hi> lies,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Colours</hi> the <hi>matter</hi> are, and <hi>ſhape</hi> the <hi>Soule;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Soule</hi> which from no ſingle part doth riſe,</l>
                     <l>But from the iuſt proportion of the <hi>whole,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And is a meere <hi>ſpirituall harmonie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of eu'ry part vnited in the <hi>Eye.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Loue</hi> is a kinde of <hi>Superſtition,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which feares the Idoll which it-ſelfe hath fram'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lust</hi> a Deſire, which rather from his <hi>owne</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Temper,</hi> then from the <hi>obiect</hi> is enflam'd;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beauty</hi> is Loues <hi>obiect, Woman</hi> Luſt's, to gaine</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Loue,</hi> Loue Deſires, <hi>Lust</hi> only to <hi>obtaine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:11"/>
                     <l>No circumſtance doth <hi>Beauty</hi> beautifie,</l>
                     <l>Like gracefull <hi>Faſhion,</hi> natiue <hi>Gomelineſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay eu'n gets pardon for <hi>Deformitie;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Art</hi> cannot it beget, but may encreaſe,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Nature</hi> had fixt <hi>Beauty</hi> perfect made,</l>
                     <l>Something ſhee left for <hi>Motion</hi> to adde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But let that <hi>Faſhion</hi> more to <hi>Modeſtie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tend, then <hi>Aſſurance; Modeſtie</hi> doth ſet</l>
                     <l>The face in his iuſt place, from <hi>Paſsions</hi> free,</l>
                     <l>Tis both the <hi>Mindes,</hi> and <hi>Bodies Beauty</hi> met;</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Modeſtie;</hi> no vertue can we ſee;</l>
                     <l>That is the Faces only <hi>Chaſtitie.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Where <hi>goodnes</hi> failes, twixt ill and ill <hi>that</hi> ſtands:</l>
                     <l>Whence tis that <hi>women</hi> though they weaker be,</l>
                     <l>And their deſires more ſtrong, yet on their hands</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Chaſtitie</hi> of <hi>men</hi> doth often lie:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lust</hi> would more common be then any one,</l>
                     <l>Could it like other ſinnes be done <hi>alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All theſe <hi>good parts</hi> a <hi>Perfect woman</hi> make,</l>
                     <l>Adde <hi>Loue</hi> to me, they make a <hi>Perfect Wife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Without Hir <hi>Loue,</hi> Hir <hi>Beauty</hi> ſhould I take</l>
                     <l>As that of <hi>Pictures,</hi> dead, <hi>That</hi> giues it life:</l>
                     <l>Till then Her <hi>Beauty</hi> like the Sunne doth ſhine</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A like</hi> to all; <hi>That</hi> makes it only <hi>mine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:11"/>
                     <l>And of that <hi>Loue,</hi> let <hi>Reaſon Father</hi> be,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Paſsion Mother;</hi> let it from the one</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Being</hi> take, the other his <hi>Degree;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Selfe loue (which ſecond Loues are built vpon,)</l>
                     <l>Will make <hi>me</hi> (if not <hi>Her)</hi> her <hi>Loue</hi> reſpect;</l>
                     <l>No Man but fauours his owne worths effect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>wiſe,</hi> ſo be Shee <hi>Fit</hi> for mee,</l>
                     <l>That is, To <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>Not to will</hi> the ſame,</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Wife</hi> is my <hi>Adopted-Selfe,</hi> and Shee</l>
                     <l>As Mee, ſo what I loue, to Loue muſt frame.</l>
                     <l>For when by Mariage both in one concurre,</l>
                     <l>Woman converts to Man, not Man to her.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <head>The Authors Epitaph.</head>
                  <l>THe Span of my daies meaſur'd, heere I rest,</l>
                  <l>That is my body; but my ſoule his guest</l>
                  <l>Is hence aſcended, whither, neither Time,</l>
                  <l>Nor Faith, nor Hope, but only loue can claime;</l>
                  <l>Where being now inlightned, Shee doth know</l>
                  <l>The Truth of all men argue of below:</l>
                  <l>Only this dust doth here in Pawne remaine,</l>
                  <l>That when the world diſſolues ſhee come againe.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="descriptions">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:12"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:12"/>
                  <head>CHARACTERS, OR VVitty Deſcriptions of the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of ſundry Perſons.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A good Woman.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Good Woman is a comfort, like a Man. Shee lacks of him nothing but heat. Thence is her ſweetnes of diſpoſition, which meets his ſtoutnes more pleaſantly; ſo wooll meets iron eaſier then iron, and turnes reſiſting into embracing. Hir greateſt learning is religion, and her thoughts are on her owne <hi>Sexe,</hi> or on men, without caſting the difference. <hi>Diſhonestie</hi> neuer comes neerer than her eares, and then wonder ſtops it out, and ſaues ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue the labour. Shee leaues the neat <hi>youth</hi> telling his <hi>luſhious</hi> tales, and puts backe the <hi>Seruingmans</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forward with a frowne: yet her kindneſſe is free enough to be ſeene; for it hath no guilt about it: and
<pb facs="tcp:20960:13"/>
her mirth is cleare, that you may looke through it, into vertue, but not beyond. She hath not behauiour at a certaine, but makes it to her occaſion. She hath ſo much knowledge as to loue it, and if ſhee haue it not at home; ſhe will fetch it; for this ſometimes in a pleaſant diſcontent ſhee dares chide her <hi>Sexe,</hi> though ſhee vſe it neuer the worſe. Shee is much within, and frames outward things to her minde, not her minde to them. Shee weares good clothes, but neuer better; for ſhee finds no degree beyond <hi>Decencie.</hi> Shee hath a content of her owne, and ſo ſeekes not a husband, but finds him. Shee is indeed moſt, but not much to deſcription, for ſhee is direct and one, and hath not the varietie of ill. Now ſhee is giuen freſh and aliue to a husband, and ſhee doth nothing more than loue him, for ſhee takes him to that purpoſe. So his good becomes the buſineſſe of her actions, and ſhee doth her ſelfe kindneſſe vpon him. After his, her chiefeſt vertue is a good husband. For <hi>Shee</hi> is <hi>Hee.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A very very Woman.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Very very Woman,</hi> is a dow-bakt man, or a Shee ment well towards man, but fell the two bowes ſhort <hi>ſtrength</hi> &amp; <hi>vnderstanding.</hi> Her virtue is the hedge of <hi>Modeſtie,</hi> that keeps a man from clyming ouer into her faults. Shee ſimpers as if ſhee had no teeth, but lips, and ſhee deuides her eyes and keeps halfe for her ſelfe, and giues th' other to her near <hi>Youth.</hi> Being ſet downe ſhee caſts her face into a platforme, which
<pb facs="tcp:20960:13"/>
dureth the meale, and is taken away with the voyder. Her draught reacheth to good manners, not to thirſt, and it is a part of their miſterie not to profeſſe hunger; but <hi>Nature</hi> takes her in priuate and ſtretcheth her vpon meat. She is <hi>Mariageable</hi> and <hi>Fourteene</hi> at once; and after ſhee doth not liue but tarry. Shee reads ouer her face euery morning, and ſomtime blots out pale, and writes red. Shee thinks ſhee is faire, though many times her opinion goes alone, and ſhee loues her glaſſe and the knight of the <hi>Sunne</hi> for lying. Shee is hid away all but her face, and that's hang'd about with toyes and deuices, like the ſigne of a Tauerne to draw <hi>Strangers.</hi> If ſhee ſhew more, ſhee preuents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and by too free-giuing, leaues no <hi>Gift.</hi> Shee may eſcape from the Seruingman, but not from the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bermaide. Shee commits with her eares for certaine, after that ſhee may goe for a Maide, but ſhee hath been lyen with in her vnderſtanding. Her <hi>Philoſophie</hi> is a ſeming neglect of thoſe, that be too good for her. Shee's a younger brother for her portion, but not for her portion of wit, that comes from her in a treble, which is ſtill too big for it; yet her <hi>Vanitie</hi> ſeldome matcheth her, with one of her owne degree, for then ſhee will beget another creature a begger, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly if ſhee marry better, ſhee marries worſe. Shee gets much by the ſimplicitie of her Sutor, and for a ieſt, laughes at him without one. Thus ſhee dreſſes a husband for her ſelfe, and after takes him for his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the land adioyning, yee may ſee it, in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingmans freſh <hi>naperie,</hi> and his leg ſteps into an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne ſtocking. I need not ſpeake of his <hi>garters,</hi> the taſſell ſhewes it ſelfe. If ſhee loue ſhee loue, ſhe loues
<pb facs="tcp:20960:14"/>
not the man but the beaſt of him. Shee is <hi>Salomons</hi> cruell creature, and a mans walking conſumption<hi>:</hi> euery caudle ſhee giues him, is a purge. Hir chiefe commendation is, ſhe brings a man to repentance.</p>
                     <div type="section">
                        <head>Her next part.</head>
                        <p>Her lightneſſe gets her to ſwim at top of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, where her wry little ſinger, bewrayes <hi>caruing;</hi> her neighbours at the latter end, know they are welcome, and for that purpoſe ſhee quencheth her thirſt. Shee trauels to and among, and ſo becomes a woman of good entertainment, for all the folly in the country, comes in cleane linnen to viſit her; ſhee breakes to them her griefe in ſugar cakes, and receiues from their mouthes in exchange, many ſtories that conclude to no purpoſe. Her eldeſt Sonne is like her howſoeuer, and that diſpraiſeth him beſt: her vtmoſt drift, is to turne him foole, which commonly ſhe obtaines at the yeares of diſcretion. Shee takes a iourney ſomtimes to her neeces houſe, but neuer thinks beyond <hi>London.</hi> Her <hi>Deuotion</hi> is good clothes, they carry her to Church, expreſſe their ſtuffe and faſhion, and are ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; if ſhee be more deuout, ſhee lifts vp a certaine number of eyes, in ſtead of prayers, and takes the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and meaſures out a nap by it, iuſt as long. Shee ſends Religion afore to <hi>Sixtie,</hi> where ſhe neuer ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes it, or driues it before her againe. Her moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie inſtruments, are a <hi>waiting-Gentlewoman,</hi> and a <hi>chamber-maide,</hi> ſhee weares her Gentlewoman ſtill, but moſt often leaues th'other in her chamber win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. She hath a litle <hi>Kennell</hi> in her lap, and ſhe ſmells
<pb facs="tcp:20960:14"/>
the ſweeter for it. The vtmoſt reach of her <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> is the fatneſſe of a Capon, and her greateſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, is the next Gentlewomans better gowne. Her moſt commendable skill, is to make her husbands fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian beare her veluet. This ſhee doth many times ouer, and then is deliuered to old age and a chaire, where euery body leaues her.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A Diſſembler</head>
                     <p>IS an eſſence needing a double definition, for hee is not that hee appeares. Vnto the eye hee is pleaſing, vnto the eare not harſh, but vnto the vnderſtanding intricate, and full of windings: he is the <hi>prima materia,</hi> and his intents giue him forme: he dieth his meanes and his meaning into two colors, he baites craft with humilitie, and his countenance is the picture of the preſent diſpoſitions. Hee winnes not by battry, but vndermining, and his racke is ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. He allures, is not allur'd by his affections, for they are the brokers of his obſeruation. Hee knowes paſſion onely by ſufferance, and reſiſteth by obeying. Hee makes his time an accomptant to his memorie, and of the humors of men weaues a net for occaſion; the inquiſitor muſt looke through his iudgment, for to the eye only he is not viſible.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:15"/>
                     <head>A Courtier</head>
                     <p>TO all mens thinking is a man, and to moſt men the fineſt: all things elſe are defined by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, but this by the ſences; but his ſureſt marke is, that hee is to bee found onely about Princes. Hee ſmells; and putteth away much of his iudgement about the ſcituation of his clothes. Hee knowes no man that is not generally knowne. His wit, like the <hi>Marigold,</hi> openeth with the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and therefore hee riſeth not before ten of the clocke. Hee puts more confidence in his words than meaning, and more in his pronuntiation than his words. <hi>Occaſion</hi> is his <hi>Cupid,</hi> and hee hath but one receipt of making loue. Hee followes nothing but inconſtancie, admires nothing but beauty, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours nothing but fortune. Loues nothing. The ſuſtenance of his diſcourſe is newes, and his cenſure like a ſhot depends vpon the charging. Hee is not, if he be out of Court, but fiſh-like breathes deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if out of his owne element. Neither his motion, or aſpect are regular, but hee mooues by the vpper <hi>Spheres,</hi> and is the reflexion of higher ſubſtances. If you finde him not heere, you ſhall in <hi>Paules,</hi> with a pick-tooth in his hat, a cape cloke, and a long ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:15"/>
                     <head>A golden Aſſe</head>
                     <p>IS a young thing, whoſe Father went to the Deuill; he is followed like a ſalt bitch, and lymb'd by him that gets vp firſt; his diſpoſition is cut, and knaues rent him like tenter-hookes: hee is as blind as his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſwallowes flatterers for friends. He is high in his owne imagination, but that imagination is a ſtone, that is raiſed by violence, deſcends naturally; when hee goes, he lookes who lookes, if he finds not good ſtore of vaylers, he comes home ſtiffe and ſeere vntill hee be new oyled and watered by his husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Whereſoeuer hee eats, hee hath an officer to warne men not to talke out of his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ment, and his owne is exceeding ſenſible, becauſe it is ſenſuall; but he cannot exchange a peece of reaſon, though hee can a peece of gold. Hee is naught pluckt, for his feathers are his beauty, and more then his beauty, they are his diſcretion, his countenance, his All. He is now at an end, for hee hath had the wolfe of vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, which he fed vntill himſelfe became the food.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:16"/>
                     <head>A Flatterer</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IS the ſhadow of a foole.</hi> Hee is a good wood-man, for he ſingleth out none but the wealthy. His cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is euer of the colour of his patient; and for his ſake he will halt or weare a wry neck. Hee diſpraiſeh nothing but pouertie, and ſmall drinke, and praiſeth his grace of making water. Hee ſelleth himſelfe with reckoning his great Friends, and teacheth the preſent how to win his praiſes by reciting the others gifts: hee is ready for all employments, but eſpecially before dinner, for his courage and his ſtomacke goe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hee will play any part vpon his countenance, and where hee cannot be admitted for a counſeller, hee will ſerue as foole. Hee frequents the court of wards and ordinaries, and fits theſe gueſts of <hi>Togae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilis,</hi> with wiues or whores. Hee entreth young men into acquaintance and debt bookes. In a word, hee is the impreſſion of the laſt terme, and will be ſo, vntill the comming of a new terme or termer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:16"/>
                     <head>Anignorant glory-hunter</head>
                     <p>IS an <hi>inſecta animalia;</hi> for he is the maggot of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, his behavuiour is another thing from himſelfe, and is glewed, and but ſet on. Hee entertaines men with repetitions, and returnes them their owne words. Hee is ignorant of nothing, no not of thoſe things, where ignorance is the leſſer ſhame. He gets the names of good wits, and vtters them for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions. Hee confeſſeth vices that he is guiltleſſe of, if they bee in faſhion; and dares not ſalute a man in old clothes, or out of faſhion. There is not a publike aſſembly without him, and hee will take any paines for an acquaintance there. In any ſhew hee will be one, though hee be but a whiſtler or a torch-bearer; and beares downe ſtrangers with the ſtorie of his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He handles nothing that is not rare, and defends his wardrope, diet, and all cuſtomes, with entitling their beginnings from Princes, great Souldiers, and ſtrange Nations. He dares ſpeake more than he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands, and adventures his words without the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of any ſeconds. He relates battels and skirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, as from an eye witnes, when his eyes theeuiſhly beguiled a ballad of them. In a word, to make ſure of admiration, he will not let himſelfe vnderſtand him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but hopes fame and opinion, will be the Readers of his Riddles.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:17"/>
                     <head>A Tymist</head>
                     <p>IS <hi>a noune Adiectiue of the preſent tenſe.</hi> He hath no more of a conſcience then Feare, and his religion is not his but the Princes. He reuerenceth a Courtiers Seruants ſeruant. Is firſt his owne Slaue, and then whoſoeuer looketh big; when hee giues hee curſeth, and when he ſells he worſhips. He reads the ſtatutes in his chamber, and weares the Bible in the ſtreets; hee neuer praiſeth any but before themſelues or friends; and miſlikes no great mans actions during his life. His new-yeares gifts are ready at <hi>Allhalomas,</hi> and the ſute he ment to mediate before them. He pleaſeth the children of great men, and promiſeth to adopt them; and his curteſie extends it ſelfe euen to the ſtable. Hee ſtraines to talke wiſely, and his modeſtie would ſerue a Bride. Hee is grauitie from the head to the foot, but not from the head to the heart; you may finde what place he affecteth, for he creepes as neere it as may be, and as paſſionately courts it; if at any time his hopes are effected, hee ſwelleth with them; and they burſt out too good for the veſſell. In a word, hee danceth to the tune of Fortune, and ſtudies for nothing but to keepe time.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:17"/>
                     <head>An Amorist</head>
                     <p>IS a creature blaſted or planet-ſtroken, and is the dog that leads blind <hi>Cupid;</hi> when hee is at the beſt, his faſhion exceeds the worth of his weight. He is neuer without verſes, and muske comfects: and ſighes to the hazard of his buttons; his eyes are all white, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to weare the liuery of his Miſtres complexion, or to keep <hi>Cupid</hi> from hitting the blacke. He fights with paſſion, and looſeth much of his bloud by his weapon; dreames, thence his palenes. His armes are careleſly vſed, as if their beſt vſe were nothing but embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. He is vntruſt and vnbuttoned, vngartred, not out of careleſnes, but care; his fartheſt end being but going to bed. Somtimes he wraps his petition in neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but it goeth not alone, for then he makes ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther qualitie moralize his affection, and his trimnes is the grace of that grace. Hir fauour lifts him vp as the Sunne moiſture; when ſhe disfauours, vnable to hold that happineſſe, it falls down in teares; his fingers are his Orators, and he expreſſeth much of himſelfe vpon ſome inſtrument. He anſwers not, or not to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and no maruell, for he is not at home. He ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth time with dancing with his Miſtres, taking vp of hir gloue, &amp; wearing hir feather; he is confinde to hir colour, &amp; dares not paſſe out of the circuit of hir me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie. His imagination is a foole, and it goeth in a pied-coat of red and white; ſhortly hee is tranſlated out of a man into folly; his imagination is the glaſſe of luſt, and himſelfe the traitor to his own diſceretion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:18"/>
                     <head>An affected Traueller</head>
                     <p>IS a ſpeaking faſhion; he hath taken paines to bee ridiculous, and hath ſeen more then he hath percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. His attire ſpeakes <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Italian,</hi> and his <hi>gate</hi> cryes <hi>Behold mee.</hi> Hee cenſures all things by countenances, and ſhrugs, and ſpeakes his owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage with ſhame and liſping: he will choake rather than confeſſe <hi>Beere</hi> good drinke: and his pick-tooth is a maine part of his behauiour. Hee chooſeth rather to be counted a <hi>Spie,</hi> then not a <hi>Polititian:</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines his reputation by naming great men familiarly. He chooſeth rather to tell lyes then not wonders, and talkes with men ſingly; his diſcourſe ſounds big but meanes nothing: and his boy is bound to admire him howſoeuer. He comes ſtill from great perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but goes with meane. He takes occaſion to ſhew lewells giuen him in regard of his vertue, that were bought in <hi>S. Martins,</hi> and not long after, hauing with a <hi>Mountebaneks</hi> method, pronounced them worth thouſands, empawneth them for a few ſhillings. Vpon feſtiuall daies he goes to Court, and ſalutes without re-ſaluting: at night in an Ordinarie hee confeſſeth the buſineſſe in hand, and ſeemes as converſant with all intents and plots, as if he begot them. His extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary accompt of men is, firſt to tell them the ends of all matters of conſequence, and then to borrow mony of them; hee offereth curteſies, to ſhew them, rather then himſelfe humble. He diſdaines all things
<pb facs="tcp:20960:18"/>
aboue his reach, and preferreth all Countries before his owne. Hee imputeth his wants and pouertie to the ignorance of the time, not his owne vnworthines: and concludes his diſcourſe with a halfe period, or a word, and leaues the reſt to imagination. In a word, his religion is faſhion, and both body and ſoule are gouerned by ſame, he loues moſt voices aboue truth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A Wiſe-man</head>
                     <p>IS the truth of the true definition of man, that is, a reaſonable creature. His diſpoſition alters, alters not. He hides himſelfe with the attire of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; and in indifferent things is content to be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them. He lookes according to nature, ſo goes his behauiour. His mind enioyes a continuall ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo cometh it, that his conſideration is alwaies at home. Hee endures the faults of all men ſilently, except his friends, and to them hee is the mirrour of their actions; by this meanes his peace commeth not from fortune, but himſelfe. He is cunning in men, not to ſurpriſe but keepe his owne, and beats off their ill affected humours, no otherwiſe then if they were flies. Hee chooſeth not friends by the ſubſidie booke, and is not luxurious after acquaintance. Hee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the ſtrength of his body, not by delicacies, but temperance; and his minde by giuing it prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence ouer his body. Hee vnderſtands things not by their forme, but qualities; and his compariſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to excuſe, but to prouoke him higher.
<pb facs="tcp:20960:19"/>
Hee is not ſubiect to caſualties, for fortune hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with the minde, except thoſe drowned in the body: but he hath diuided his ſoule, from the caſe of his ſoule, whoſe weakneſſe he aſſiſts no otherwiſe than commiſeratiuely, not that it is his, but that it is. Hee is thus, and will be thus: and liues ſubiect neither to time nor his frailties; the ſeruant of vertue, and by vertue the friend of the higheſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A noble Spirit</head>
                     <p>HAth ſurueyed and fortified his diſpoſition, and converts all occurrents into experience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween which experience and his reaſon, there is a mariage; the iſſue are his actions. He circuits his intents, and ſeeth the end before he ſhoot. Men are the inſtruments of his Art, and there is no man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his vſe: occaſion encites him, none enticeth him; and hee mooues by affection, not for affection; hee loues glory, skornes ſhame, and gouerneth and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with one countenance; for it comes from one conſideration. He calls not the varietie of the world chances, for his meditation hath trauailed ouer them; and his eye mounted vpon his vnderſtanding ſeeth them as things vnderneath. Hee couers not his bodie with delicacies, nor excuſeth theſe delicacies by his bodie, but teacheth it, ſince it is not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it's owne imbecilitie to ſhew or ſuffer. He licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not his weaknes, to weare fate, but knowing rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be no idle gift of nature, he is the Steeres-man
<pb facs="tcp:20960:19"/>
of his owne deſtinie. Truth is his Goddeſſe, and hee takes pains to get her, not to looke like hir. He knowes the condition of the world, that he muſt act one thing by another, and then another. To theſe he carries his deſires, not his deſires him; and ſtickes not faſt by the way (for that contentment is repentance) but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the circle of all courſes, of all intents, of all things, to haue but one center or period, without all diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he haſteth thither and ends there, as his true and naturall element. Hee doth not contemne fortune, but not confeſſe her. He is no Gamſter of the world (which onely complaine and praiſe her) but being only ſenſible of the honeſtie of actions, contemnes a particular profit as the excrement or skum. Vnto the ſocietie of men hee is a <hi>Sunne,</hi> whoſe cleareneſſe directs their ſteps in a regular motion: when he is more particular, hee is the wiſe-mans freind, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the indifferent, the medicine of the vicious. Thus time goeth not from him, but with him: and he feeles age more by the ſtrength of his ſoule, than the weakneſſe of his body: thus feeles he not paine, but eſteemes all ſuch things as frends that deſire to file off his fetters, and helpe him out of priſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>An old Man</head>
                     <p>IS a thing that hath been a man in his daies. Old men are to bee knowne blindfolded: for their talke is as terrible as their reſemblance. They praiſe their
<pb facs="tcp:20960:20"/>
owne times as vehemently, as if they would ſell them. They become wrinckled with frowning and facing youth: they admire their owne cuſtomes, euen to the eating of red herring, and going wet-ſhod. They call the thombe vnder the girdle grauitie, and becauſe they can hardly ſmel at all, their poſies are vnder their girdles. They count it an ornament of ſpeech, to cloſe the period with a cough; and it is venerable, they ſay, to ſpend time in wyping their driueled beards. Their diſcourſe is vnanſwerable, by reaſon of their obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: and their ſpeech is much, though little to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Truthes and lyes paſſe with an equall affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for their memories ſeuerall is worne into one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle, and ſo they come out with one ſenſe. They teach their ſeruants their duties with as much ſcorne &amp; tyrannie, as ſome people teach their dogs to fetch. Their enuie is one of their diſeaſes. They put off and on their clothes, with that certaintie, as if they knew, their heads would not direct them, and therefore cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſhould. They take a pride in halting and going ſtiffely, and therefore their ſtaues are carued and tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; they truſt their attire with much of their graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and they dare not go without a gown in ſummer. Their hats are bruſhed to draw mens eyes off from their faces; but of all, their <hi>Pomanders</hi> are worne to moſt purpoſe, for their putri fied breath ought not to want either a ſmell to defend, or a dog to excuſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:20"/>
                     <head>A Country Gentleman</head>
                     <p>IS a thing out of whoſe corruption, the generation of a Iuſtice of peace is produced. Hee ſpeakes ſtatutes and husbandry well enough, to make his neighbours thinke him a wiſe-man; hee is well skilled in <hi>Arithmetike</hi> or rates; and hath eloquence enough to ſaue his two-pence. His converſation amongſt his Tenants is deſperate; but amongſt his equalls full of doubt. His trauell is ſeldome farther then the next market towne, and his inquiſition is about the price of corne: when hee trauelleth hee will goe ten mile out of the way, to a Coſens houſe of his to ſaue charges; and rewards the Seruanrs by taking them by the hand when hee departs. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnder a <hi>Sub-poena</hi> can draw him to <hi>London,</hi> and when hee is there, hee ſtickes faſt vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie obiect, caſts his eyes away vpon gazing, and becomes the prey of euery cut-purſe. When he comes home thoſe wonders ſerue him for his holliday talke. If hee goes to Court, it is in yellow ſtockings, and if he be in winter, in a ſleight taffetie cloke, &amp; pumpes and pantaſtles. He is chaynd,
<pb facs="tcp:20960:21"/>
that wooes the vſher fo his comming into the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, where hee becomes troubleſome with the ill managing of his rapier, and the wearing of his girdle of one faſhion and the hangers of another; by this time hee hath learned to kiſſe his hand, and make a leg both together, and the names of Lords and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors; he hath thus much toward entertainment and curtefie, but of the laſt he makes more vſe; for by the recitall of <hi>my Lord,</hi> hee coniures his poore country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But this is not his element, but he muſt home againe, being like a Dor, that ends his flight in a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A fine Gentleman</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IS the Cynamon tree,</hi> whoſe barke is more worth then his body. Hee hath read the booke of good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and by this time each of his limbes may read it. He alloweth of no iudge, but the eye; pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, boulſtring and bombaſting are his <hi>Orators:</hi> by theſe alſo he proues his induſtrie: for he hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed legs, haire, beauty, and ſtraightneſſe, more then nature left him. Hee vnlocks maidenheads with his language, and ſpeakes <hi>Ephues</hi> not ſo gracefully as heartily. His diſcourſe makes not his behauiour, but he buyes it at Court, as countrymen their clothes in Burchin lane. Hee is ſomwhat like the <hi>Salamander,</hi> and liues in the flame of loue, which paines he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth comically<hi>:</hi> and nothing grieues him ſo much, as the want of a Poet to make an iſſue in his loue; yet he
<pb facs="tcp:20960:21"/>
ſighes ſweetly, and ſpeakes lamentably: for his breath is perfumed, and his words are winde. Hee is beſt in ſeaſon at Chriſtmas; for the Boores head and Reuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler come together; his hopes are laden in his qualitie, and leſt fidlers ſhould take him vnprouided, he weares pumpes in his pocket, and leſt hee ſhould take fidlers vnprouided, he whiſtles his owne galliard. He is a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender of ten yeares, and mariage ruſts him. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards hee maintaines himſelfe an implement of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold by caruing and vſhering. For all this he is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall only in Tailors and Barbers, but his opinion is euer ready and euer idle. If you will know more of his Arts, the Brokers ſhop is the witnes of his valour, where lies wounded, dead, rent and out of faſhion many a ſpruce ſuite ouerthrowen by his fantaſtikenes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>An elder Brother.</head>
                     <p>IS a creature borne to the beſt aduantage of things without him; that hath the ſtart at the beginning, but loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers it away before the ending. He lookes like his land, as heauily, and durtily, as ſlubbornely. He dares doe any thing but fight: and feares nothing but his Fathers life and minoritie. The firſt thing hee makes knowne is his eſtate; and the load-ſtone that drawes him is the vpper end of the table. He wooeth by a particular, and his ſtrongeſt argument is the ioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. His obſeruation is all about the faſhion, and he commends Partlets for a rare deuiſe. Hee ſpeakes
<pb facs="tcp:20960:22"/>
no language, but ſmells of dogs or hawkes; and his ambition flies Iuſtice-hight. He loues to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and hee will goe into the kitchin, but heele haue it. He loues glory, but is ſo lazie as he is content with flatterie. He ſpeakes moſt of the precedencie of age, and proteſts fortune the greateſt vertue. He ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the old ſeruants, and tells what ſtrange acts hee will doe, when he raignes. Hee verily beleeues houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers the beſt common-wealths men; and therfore ſtudies baking, brewing, greaſing, and ſuch, as the lyms of goodneſſe. Hee iudgeth it no ſmall ſigne of wiſdome to talke much, his tongue therefore goes continually his errand, but neuer ſpeeds. If his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding were not honeſter than his will, no man ſhould keepe a good conceit by him; for hee thinkes it no theft, to ſell all he can to opinion. His pedigree and his fathers ſeale-ring, are the ſtilts of his crazed diſpoſition. He had rather keep companie with the dregs of men, than not to be the beſt man. His in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuation is the inviting men to his houſe; and hee thinkes it a great modeſtie, to comprehend his cheere vnder a peece of mutton and a rabbet; if by this time he be not knowne, hee will goe home againe, for hee can no more abide to haue himſelfe concealed, then his land; yet he is as you ſee good for nothing, except to make a ſtallion to maintaine the race.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:22"/>
                     <head>A Welchman</head>
                     <p>IS the Oyſter, that the pearle is in, for a man may be pickt out of him. He hath the abilities of the mind in <hi>potentia,</hi> and <hi>actu</hi> nothing but boldneſſe. His clothes are in faſhion before his bodie; and hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts boldneſſe the chiefeſt vertue. Aboue all men he loues a Herrald, and ſpeakes pedigrees naturally. He accompts none well deſcended, that call him not Coſen: and prefers <hi>Owen Glendower</hi> before any of the nine Worthies. The firſt note of his familiaritie is the confeſſion of his valour; and ſo he preuents quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells. Hee voucheth Welch a pure, an vnconquered language; and courts Ladies with the ſtorie of their Chronicle. To conclude, he is pretious in his owne conceit, and vpon <hi>S. Dauids</hi> day without compariſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>A Pedant</head>
                     <p>HE treads in rule, and one hand skans verſes, and the other holds his ſcepter. He dares not thinke a thought, that the Nominatiue caſe gouernes not the verbe; and he neuer had meaning in his life, for he trauelled onely for words. His ambition is <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſme,</hi> and his example is <hi>Tully.</hi> Hee values phraſes, and elects them by the found, and the eight parts of ſpeach are his ſeruants. To be briefe, he is a <hi>Hetaro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clue,</hi> for he wants the plurall number, hauing onely the ſingle qualitie of words.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:23"/>
                     <head>A Seruingman</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IS a Creature which though he be not drunke, yet is not his owne man.</hi> He tells without asking, who ownes him, by the ſuperſcription of his liuery. His life is for eaſe and leaſure much about gentleman-like. His wealth enough to ſuffice nature, and ſufficient to make him happy, if hee were ſure of it; for hee hath litle and wants nothing, he values himſelfe higher or lower, as his Maſter is. Hee hates or loues the men, as his Maſter doth the Maſter. He is commonly proud of his Maſters horſes, or his Chriſtmas; hee ſleepes when he is ſleepie, is of his religion, onely the clocke of his ſtomacke is ſet to goe an hower after his. He ſeldome breakes his owne clothes. He neuer drinkes but double, for hee muſt be pledg'd: not commonly without ſome ſhort ſentence nothing to the purpoſe: and ſeldome abſtaines till hee come to a thirſt. His diſcretion is to bee carefull for his Maſters credit, and his ſufficiencie to marſhall diſhes at a table, and to carue well. His neatneſſe conſiſts much in his haire and outward linnen. His courting language, viſible bawdy ieſts; and againſt his matter faile, he is alway ready furniſhed with a ſong. His inheritance is the chamber-maide, but often purchaſeth his Maſters daughter, by reaſon of opportunitie, or for want of a better; he alwaies cuckolds himſelfe, and neuer mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries but his own widow. His Maſter being appeaſed, he becomes a retayner, and entailes himſelfe and his poſteritie vpon his heires males for euer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:23"/>
                     <head>An Host</head>
                     <p>IS the kernell of a ſigne: or the ſigne is the ſhell, and mine Hoſt is the ſnaile. He conſiſts of double beere and fellowſhip, and his vices are the bawdes of his thirſt. Hee entertaines humbly, and giues his gueſts power, aſwell of himſelfe as houſe. Hee anſwers all mens expectations to his power, ſaue in the recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and hath gotten the tricke of greatneſſe, to lay all miſlikes vpon his ſeruants. His wife is the <hi>Cumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeede</hi> of his doue houſe: and to bee a good gueſt is a warrant for her libertie. Hee traffiques for gueſts by mens friends, friends friend, and is ſenſible only of his purſe. In a word, he is none of his owne: for he nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eats, drinks or thinks but at other mens charges and appointments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="description">
                     <head>An Oſtler</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IS a thing that ſcrubbeth vnreaſonably his horſe, reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably himſelfe.</hi> He conſiſts of Trauellers, though he be none himſelfe. His higheſt ambition is to bee Hoſt, and the invention of his ſigne is his greateſt wit: for the expreſſing whereof he ſends away the painters forwant of vnderſtanding. He hath certain charmes for a horſe mouth, that hee ſhall not eat his hay: and behind your backe, hee will cozen your horſe to his face. His curry-combe is one of his beſt parts, for hee
<pb facs="tcp:20960:24"/>
expreſſeth much by the gingling: and his mane-combe is a Spinners card turn'd out of ſeruice. Hee puffes and blowes ouer your horſe, to the hazard of a double iugge: and leaues much of the dreſſing to the prouerbe of <hi>Muli mut uo ſcabient,</hi> one horſe rubs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He comes to him that calls loudeſt not firſt; he takes a broken head patiently, but the knaue he feeles not. His vtmoſt honeſtie is goodfellowſhip, and hee ſpeakes Northerne, what countryman ſoeuer. Hee hath a penſion of Ale from the next <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Sadler</hi> for intelligence. Hee loues to ſee you ride, and holds your ſtirrop in expectation.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="news">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>NEWES,</hi> FROM ANY VVHENCE: OR Old Truthes vnder a ſuppoſall of <hi>Noueltie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head>Occaſioned by diuers Eſſayes and priuate <hi>paſſages of wit between ſundry Gentlemen</hi> vpon that ſubiect.</head>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Newes from Court.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is thought heere, that there are as great miſeries beyond happineſſe, as a this ſide it, as <hi>being in loue.</hi> That truth is euery mans by aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. That time makes euery thing aged, and yet it ſelfe was neuer but a minute old. That next ſleep, the greateſt deuourer of time is buſineſſe: the greateſt ſtretcher of it, <hi>Paſsion;</hi> the trueſt meaſure of it, <hi>Contemplation.</hi> To be ſaued, alwaies is the beſt plot: and vertue alwaies cleeres her way as ſhe goes. <hi>Vice</hi> is euer behind-hand with it ſelfe; that <hi>wit</hi> and a <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> are two fraile things, and both the frailer by concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. That the meanes of begetting a man hath more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſt mankind then the end. That the madnes of loue
<pb facs="tcp:20960:25"/>
is to be ſicke of one part, and cured by another. The mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ielouſie, that it is ſo diligent, and yet hopes to looſe his labour. That all women for the bodily part, are but the ſame meaning put in diuers words; that the difference in the ſenſe is their vnderſtanding. That the wiſdome of <hi>Action</hi> is <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> the knowledge of contemplation is truth, the knowledge of action is men. That the firſt conſiders what ſhould be, the latter makes vſe of what is. That euery man is weake in his owne humors. That eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie man a litle beyond himſelfe is a foole. That affectation is the more ridiculous part of folly, then ignorance. That the matter of greatneſſe is compariſon. That God made one world of <hi>Subſtances;</hi> man hath made another of <hi>Arte</hi> and <hi>Opinion.</hi> That money is nothing but a thing which Art hath turned vp trumpe. That cuſtome is the ſoule of circumſtances. That cuſtome hath ſo far preuailed, that truth is now the greateſt newes.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>T. O.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Anſwer to the Court newes.</head>
                     <p>THat <hi>Happines</hi> and <hi>Miſerie</hi> are <hi>Antipodes.</hi> That <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is not <hi>Felicitie,</hi> but the rode thither. That mans ſtrength is but a viciſitude of falling and riſing. That only to refraine ill, is to be ill ſtill. That the plot of ſaluation was laid before the plot of <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> That en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying is the preparatiue to contemning. That hee that ſeekes opinion beyond merit, goes iuſt ſo far backe. That no man can obtaine his deſires; nor the world hath not to fill his meaſure. That to ſtudie men is more profitable than bookes. That mens loues are their afflictions. That
<pb facs="tcp:20960:25"/>
titles of honour are tartles to ſtill ambition. That to be a King is fames <hi>butt,</hi> and feares <hi>quiuer.</hi> That the ſoules of women and louers are wrapt vp in the portmanque of their ſenſes. That imagination is the end of man. That wit is the web, and wiſdome the wooſe of the cloth, ſo that womens ſoules were neuer made vp. That enuy knowes what it will not confeſſe. That <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> is like the art proſpectiue, one point center, begetting infinite rayes. That man, woman, and the deuill, are the three degrees of compariſon. That this newes holds number but not weight, by which couple all things receiue forme.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>A. S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Country Newes.</head>
                     <p>THat there is moſt heere, for it gathers in going. That reputation is meaſured by the acre. That pouertie is the greateſt diſhoneſtie. That the pitty of <hi>(alas poore ſoule)</hi> is for the moſt part miſtaken. That roſt beefe is the beſt ſmell. That a Iuſtice of peace is the laſt relique of Idolatry. That the allegorie of Iuſtice drawne blind, is turned the wrong way. That not to liue to heauenly, is accounted great wrong. That wiſdome deſcends in a race. That we loue names better than perſons. That to hold in knights-ſeruice is a ſlipperie tenure. That a Papiſt is a new word for a traytor. That the dutie of religion is lent not pai'd. That the reward is loſt in the want of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. That the Puritane perſecution is as a cloud that can hide the glory of the light, but not the day. That the emulation of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> to bee the <hi>Kings</hi> country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:20960:26"/>
thruſt the honour on the <hi>Welch.</hi> That a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier neuer attaines his ſelfe knowledge but by report. That his beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> is a hearne dogge. That many great men are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> they know not their own Fathers. That loue is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> worme. That a woman is the effect of her owne firſt ſame. That to remember, to know, and to vnderſtand, are three degrees not vnderſtood. That country ambition is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, for there is nothing aboue a man. That fighting i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> a Seruingmans valour, martyrdom their Maſters. That to liue long is to fill vp the daies wee liue. That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ale of ſome mens religion reflects from their friends. That the pleaſure of vice is indulgence of the preſent, for it endures but the acting. That the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perreward of goodneſſe is from within, the externall is pollicie. That good and ill is the croſſe and pile in the game of life. That the ſoule is the lampe of the body, reaſon of the ſoule, religion of reaſon, faith of religion, Chriſt of faith. That circumſtances are the atomies of policie, cenſure the being, action the life, but ſucceſſe the ornament. That authoritie preſſeth downe with weight and is thought violence: policie trips vp the heeles and is called dexteritie. That this life is a throng in a narrow paſſage, hee that is firſt out finds eaſe, hee in the middle worſt, hemb'd in with troubles, the hindmoſt that driues both our afore him, though not ſuffering wrong, hath his part in doing it. That God requires of our debts a recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not payment. That heauen is the eaſieſt purchaſe, for wee are the richer for the disburſing. That liberalitie ſhould haue no obiect but the poore, if our minds were rich. That the miſterie of greatneſſe is to keep the inferior ignorant of it. That all this is no newes to a better wit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>That the Citie cares not what the Country thinks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. T. R.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:26"/>
                     <head>Newes from the very Country.</head>
                     <p>THat it is a fripery of Courtiers, Merchants, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which haue been in faſhion, and are very neere worne out. That Iuſtices of peace haue the felling of vnderwoods, but the Lords haue the great falls. That Ieſuits are like Apricocks, heretofore here and there one ſuccour'd in a great mans houſe and coſt deare, now you may haue them for nothing in euery cottage. That euery great vice is a Pike in a pond that deuoures vertues and leſſe vices. That it is wholſomeſt getting a ſtomacke, by walking on your own ground: &amp; the thriftieſt laying of it at anothers table. That debtors are in <hi>London</hi> cloſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and here haue the libertie of the houſe. That <hi>Atheists</hi> in affliction, like blind beggers, are forced to aske though they know not of whom. That there are (God be thanked) not two ſuch acres in all the country, as the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter-hall.</hi> That only Chriſtmas Lords know their ends. That w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omen are not ſo tender fruit, but that they doe as well and beare as well vpon beds, as plaſhed againſt walls. That our carts are neuer worſe employed, than when they are wayted on by coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. That ſentences in Authors like haires in an horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, concurre in one roote of beauty and ſtrength, but being pluckt out one by one, ſerue onely for ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and ſnares. That both want and abundance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually aduance a rectified man from the world, as cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and ſtones are both good caſting for an hawke. That I am ſure there is none of the forbidden fruit left, becauſe we doe not all eat thereof. That our beſt three pilde miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe
<pb facs="tcp:20960:27"/>
comes from beyond the ſea, and rides poſt through the country, but his errand is to Court: That next to no wife and children, your owne wife and children are beſt paſtime, anothers wife and your children worſe, your wife and anothers children worſt. That Stateſmen hunt their fortunes, and are often at default: Fauorites courſe her and are euer in view. That intemperance is not ſo vnwholeſome heere; for none euer ſaw Sparrow ſicke of the pox. That here is no trechery nor fidelitie, but it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe here are no ſecrets. That Court motions are vp and down, our<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> circular: theirs like ſquibs cannot ſtay at the higheſt, nor returne to the place which they roſe from, but vaniſh &amp; we are out in the way, Ours like mill-wheels buſie without changing place; they haue peremptorie fortunes, we viciſſitudes.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>I. D.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Anſwer to the very Country Newes.</head>
                     <p>IT is thought heere, that man is the coole of time, and made dreſſer of his owne fatting. That the fine Sences are Cinque ports for temptation, the trafficke ſinne, the Lieutenant <hi>Sathan,</hi> the cuſtome tribute, ſoules. That the Citizens of the high Court grow rich by ſimplicitie: but thoſe of <hi>London</hi> by ſimple craft. That life, death and time, doe with ſhort cudgels dance the Matachiue. That thoſe which dwell vnder the <hi>Zona Torrida,</hi> are troubled with more damps, than thoſe of <hi>Frigida.</hi> That <hi>Policie</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> hath of late hir maſque rent from her face, and ſhe is found with a wry mouth and a ſtinking breath, and thoſe that courted her hotly, hate her now in the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:20960:27"/>
degree, or beyond. That nature too much louing her owne, becomes vnnaturall and fooliſh. That the ſoule in ſome is like an egge, hatched by a young pullet, who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten rigging from her neſt, makes hot and cold beget rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe, which her wanton youth will not beleeue, till the faire ſhell being broken, the ſtinke appeareth to profit others, but cannot her. That thoſe are the wiſe ones, that hold the ſuperficies of vertue, to ſupport her contrary and all-ſufficient. That clemencie within and without is the nurſe of rebellion. That thought of the future is retired into the country, and time preſent dwels at Court. That I liuing neere the churchyard, where many are buried of the peſt, yet my infection commeth from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and it is feared it will diſperſe further into the kingdome.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>A. S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Newes to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie.</head>
                     <p>A Meere Scholler, is but a liue booke. Action doth expreſſe knowledge, better then words; ſo much of the ſoule is loſt, as the body cannot vtter. To teach ſhould rather be an effect, then the purpoſe of learning. Age decaies nature, perfects Arte: therefore the glory of youth, is ſtrength of the gray head, wiſdome; yet moſt condemne the follies of their owne infancie, runne after thoſe of the worlds, and in reuerence of antiquitie will beare an old error againſt a new truth. <hi>Logick</hi> is the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldry</hi> of Arts, the array of iudgment; none it ſelfe, nor any ſcience without it<hi>:</hi> where it and learning meet not, muſt bee either a skilfull ignorance, or a wilde knowledge. Vnderſtanding cannot conclude out of moode and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. Diſcretion conteines <hi>Rhetorique;</hi> the next way
<pb facs="tcp:20960:28"/>
to learne good words, is to learne ſenſe; the neweſt <hi>Philoſophie</hi> is ſoundeſt, the eldeſt <hi>Diuinitie: Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie</hi> begins in nature, ends in magicke. There is no honeſtie of the body without health, which no man hath had ſince <hi>Adam. Intemperance</hi> that was the firſt mother of ſickneſſe, is now the daughter. Nothing dies but qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. No kinde in the world can periſh without ruine of the whole. All parts helpe one another (like States) for particular intereſt. So in arts which are but tranſlations of nature. There is no ſound poſition in any one, which, imagine falſe, there may not from it bee drawne ſtrong concluſions, to diſproue all the reſt. Where one truth is granted, it may be by direct meanes brought to confirme any other controverted. The ſoule and body of the firſt man, were made fit to be immortall together, we cannot liue to the one, but we muſt dye to the other. A man and a Chriſtian are two creatures. Our perfection in this world is vertue, in the next knowledge, when wee ſhall read the glory of God in his owne face.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Newes from Sea.</head>
                     <p>THat the beſt pleaſure is to haue no obiect of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and vniformitie is a better proſpect then varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. That putting to Sea is change of life but not of condition<hi>:</hi> where riſings and falls calmes and croſſegales are yours in order and by turne, forewinds but by chance. That it is the worſt winde to haue no winde, and that your ſmooth-fac'd Courtiers deading your courſe by a calme, giues greater impediment, then an open aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries croſſe-gale. That leuitie is a vertue, for many are
<pb facs="tcp:20960:28"/>
held vp by it That its nothing ſo intricate &amp; infinite to rig a ſhip as a woman, and the more either is fraught, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to leake. That to pumpe the one and ſhreeue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is alike noyſome. That ſmall faults habituated are as dangerous as little leakes vnfound, and that to puniſh and not preuent, is to labour in the pumpe, and leaue the leake open. That it is beſt ſtricking ſaile before a ſtorme, and neceſſarieſt in it. That a little time in our life is beſt, as the ſhorteſt cutt to our hauen is the happieſt voyage. That to him that hath no Hauen no winde, is frendly, and yet it is better to haue no Hauen, then ſome kind of one. That expedition is euery where to bee bribed but at Sea. That gaine workes this miracle to make men walke vpon the water, and that the ſound of commoditie drownes the noiſe of a ſtorme, eſpecially of an abſent one. That I haue once in my life out gon night at Sea, but neuer darkneſſe: and that I ſhall neuer wonder to ſee a hard world, becauſe I haue liued to ſee the Sunne a bankerout, being ready to ſtarue for cold in his perpetuall preſence. That a mans companions are (like ſhips) to be kept in diſtance, for fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling foule one of another, only with my friend I will cloſe. That the faireſt field for a running head is the Sea, where he may runne himſelfe out of breath, and his humor out of him. That I could carry you much further, and yet leaue more before then behind, and all will be but <hi>via Nauis,</hi> without print or tracke, for ſo is morall inſtruction to youthes watriſh humor. That though a ſhip vnder ſaile bee a good ſight, yet it is a better to ſee her moor'd in the Hauen. That I care not what become of this fraile Barcke of my fleſh, ſo I ſaue the paſſenger. And heere I caſt anchor.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="news">
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:29"/>
                  <head>Forrein Newes of the yeere 1604.</head>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>From France.</head>
                     <p>IT is deliuered from <hi>France</hi> that the choice of friends there is as of their wines, thoſe that being new, are hard and harſh, proue beſt; the moſt pleaſing are leaſt laſting. That an enemie fierce at the firſt on ſet is as a torrent tumbling down a mountaine; a while it beares all before it, haue but that whiles patience you may paſſe it dry-foot. That a penetrating iudgment may enter into a mans minde by his bodies gate; if this appeare affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, apiſh, and vnſtable; a wonder if that bee ſetled. That vaine-glory, new faſhions and the <hi>French</hi> diſeaſe are vpon termes of quitting their Countries allegance to bee made free Deniſons of <hi>England.</hi> That the wounds of ancient enmities haue their ſcars which cannot bee ſo well cloſed to the ſight but they will lye open to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie. That a Princes pleaſurable vices vſhered by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and waited on by conuinence, ſooner puniſh themſelues by the ſubiects imitation, then they can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by remonſtrance or correction, ſo apt are ill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to rebound on them that giue them. That Kings heare truth oftener for the tellers then their owne aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <pb facs="tcp:20960:29"/>
                     <head>From Spaine.</head>
                     <p>THat the ſhorteſt cutt to the riches of the Indies is by their contempt. That who is feared of moſt, feares moſt. That it more vexeth the proud that men deſpiſe them, then that they not feare them. That great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is fruitfull enough, when other helpes faile, to beget on it ſelfe deſtruction. That it is a groſſe flattering of ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red crueltie to honeſt it with the title of clemencie. That to eat much at other mens coſt and little at his own is the wholſomeſt and moſt nouriſhing dyet both in Court and country. That thoſe are apteſt to dominere ouer others who by ſuffering indignities haue learned to offer them. That ambition like a ſeeled Doue flies vp to fall downe, it mindes not whence it came but whither it will. That euen Gally-ſlaues ſetting light by their captiuitie, finde freedome in bondage. That to be ſlow in militarie buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes is to bee ſo courteous as to giue the way to an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. That lightning and greatnes more feare then hurt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>From Rome.</head>
                     <p>THat the venereall (called veniall) ſinne is to paſſe in the rank of Cardinall vertues, and that thoſe ſhould bee held henceforth his Holineſſe beneficiall frends that ſin vpon hope of pardon. That where vice is a ſtate-commoditie, hee is an offender that often offends not. That Iewes and Curtezans there, are as beaſts that men feed to feed on. That for an Engliſhman to abide at <hi>Rome</hi> is not ſo dangerous as report makes it, ſince it skills
<pb facs="tcp:20960:30"/>
not where we liue ſo wee take heed how we liue. That greatneſſe comes not downe by the way it went vp, there being often found a ſmall diſtance between the higheſt and the loweſt fortunes. That tackt authoritie is oft leſſe at home then abroad regarded, while things that ſeeme, are (commonly) more a far off then neere hand feared.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>From <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice.</head>
                     <p>THat the moſt profitable bancke is the true vſe of a mans ſelfe, while ſuch as grow mouldy in idleneſſe make their houſes their toombes and dye before their death. That many dangerous ſpirits lye buried in their wants, which had they meanes to their minds would dare as much as thoſe that with their better fortunes ouer-top them. That profeſſed Curtezans if they be any way good, it is becauſe they are openly bad. That frugalitie is the richeſt treaſure of an Eſtate, where men feed for hunger, clothe for cold and modeſtie, &amp; ſpend for honor, charitie, and ſafetie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>From Germanie.</head>
                     <p>THat the infectious vice of drunken goodfellowſhip is like to ſticke by that Nation as long as the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of offendors benums the ſenſe of offending, and that a common blot is held no ſtayne. That diſcretions muſt bee taken by weight not taile: who doth otherwiſe, ſhall both prooue his owne too light and fall ſhort of his reckoning. That feare and a nice forecaſt of euery ſleight danger ſeldom giues either faithfull or fruitfull counſell.
<pb facs="tcp:20960:30"/>
That the Empire of <hi>Germanie</hi> is not more great then that ouer a mans ſelfe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>From the Low Countries.</head>
                     <p>THat one of the ſureſt grounds of a mans libertie is, not to giue another power ouer it. That the moſt dangerous plunge wherto to put thine enemie is deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> while forcing him to ſet light by his owne life, thou makeſt him maſter of thine. That neglected danger lights ſooneſt and heauieſt. That they are wiſeſt who in the likelyhood of good, prouide for ill. That ſince pitty dwells at the next doore to miſerie, he liueth moſt at eaſe that is neighboured with enuie. That the euill fortune of the wars as well as the good is variable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Newes from my Lodging.</head>
                     <p>THat the beſt proſpect is to looke inward. That it is quieter ſleeping in a good conſcience then a whole skin. That a ſoule in a fat bodie lies ſoft, and is loth to riſe. That he muſt riſe betimes who would coſen the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. That <hi>Flatterie</hi> is increaſed from a pillow vnder the elbow, to a bed vnder the whole bodie. That <hi>Policie</hi> is the vnſleeping night of reaſon. That hee who ſleepes in the cradle of ſecuritie, ſins ſoundly without ſtarting. That guilt is the flea of the conſcience. That no man is throughly awaked but by affliction. That a hang'd chamber in priuate is nothing ſo convenient as a hang'd Traitor in publique. That the religion of <hi>Papiſtry,</hi> is like a curtaine made to keep out the light. That the life of moſt
<pb facs="tcp:20960:31"/>
women is walking in their ſleepe, and they talke their dreames. That chambering is counted a ciuiler qualitie, then playing at tables in the Hall, though Seruingmen vſe both. That the beſt bedfellow for all times in the yeere is a good bed without a fellow. That he who tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in a calme bed, hath his tempeſt within. That hee who will riſe, muſt firſt lye downe, and take humilitie in his way. That ſleep is deaths picture drawne to life, or the twilight of life and death. That in ſleep wee kindly ſhake death by the hand, but when wee are awaked wee will not know him. That often ſleeping are ſo many try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls to die, that at laſt we may doe it perfectly. That few dare write the true newes of their chamber, and that I haue none ſecret enough to tempt a ſtrangers curioſitie, or a ſeruants diſcouerie. <hi>God giue you good morrow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>B. R.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Newes of my morning worke.</head>
                     <p>THat to bee good is the way to bee moſt alone or the beſt accompanied. That the way to heauen is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken for the moſt melancholy walke. That moſt feare the worlds opinion more then Gods diſpleaſure. That a Court friend ſeldom goes further then the firſt degree of charitie. That the deuill is the perfecteſt Courtier. That innocency was firſt cozen to man, now guiltineſſe hath the neereſt allyance. That ſleep is deaths leger Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor. That time can neuer bee ſpent: wee paſſe by it and cannot returne. That none can be ſure of more time then an inſtant. That ſin makes worke for repentance or the deuill. That patience hath more power then afflictions. That euery ones memorie is diuided into two parts: the
<pb facs="tcp:20960:31"/>
part looſing all is the ſea, the keeping part is land. That honeſtie in the Court liues in perſecution like Proteſtants in Spaine. That predeſtination and conſtancie are alike vncerteine to be iudged of. That reaſon makes loue the Seruingman. That vertues fauour is better then a Kings fauorite. That being ſick begins a ſute to God, being well poſſeſſeth it. That health is the coach which caries to heauen, ſicknes the poſt-horſe. That worldly delights to one in extreame ſicknes is like a hiecandle to a blind man. That abſence doth ſharpen loue, preſence ſtrengthens it, that the one brings fuell, the other blowes till it burnes cleere, that loue often breaks friendſhip, that euer increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth loue. That conſtancie in women and loue in men is alike rare. That Arte is truths iugler. That falſhood playes a larger part in the world then truth. That blinde zeale and lame knowledge are alike apt to ill. That for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is humbleſt where moſt contemned. That no porter but reſolution keeps feare out of minds. That the face of goodnes without a body is the worſt wickedneſſe. That weomens fortunes aſpire but by others powers. That a man with a female wit is the worſt <hi>Hermaphrodite.</hi> That a man not worthy being a frend, wrongs himſelf by being an acquaintance. That the worſt part of ignorance is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good and ill ſeem alike. That all this is newes onely to fooles.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>M<hi rend="sup">r••</hi>. B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Newes from the lower end of the Table.</head>
                     <p>IT is ſaid among the folkes heere, that if a man dye in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, he hath onely broke his fast in this world: If in his youth, hee hath left vs at dinner. That it is bed-time with a
<pb facs="tcp:20960:32"/>
man at thereſcore and ten; and he that liues to a hundred yeeres hath walked a mile after ſupper. That the humble-minded man makes the lowest curtſie. That grace before meat is our election before we were; grace after, our ſaluation when we are gone. The ſoule that halts between two opinions, falls between two ſtooles. That a foole at the vpper end of the table is the bread before the ſalt. He that hates to be reproued ſits in his owne light. Hunger is the cheapest ſawce and nature the chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest gueſt. The ſenſible man and the ſilent woman are the beſt diſcourſers. Repentance without amendment is but the ſhifting of a foule trencher: He that tells a lye to ſaue his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, wipes his mouth with his ſleeue to ſpare his napkin. The tongue of aieſter is the fiddle that the bearts of the companie dance to. The tongue of a foole carues a peece of his heart to euery man ſits next him. A ſilent man is a couered meſſe. The contented man onely is his owne caruer. Hee that hath many friends eats too much ſalt with his meat. That wit without diſcretion cuts other men meat and his own fingers. That the ſoule of a cholericke man ſits euer by the fire ſide. That patience is the larde to the leane meat of aduerſitie. The Epicure puts his money into his belly, and the miſer his belly into his purſe. That the best companie makes the vpper end of the table, and not the ſaltſeller. The ſuperſluitie of a mans poſſeſsions is the broken meat that ſhould remaine to the poore. That the enuious keeps his knife in his hand and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes his meat whole. A rich foole among the wiſe is a gilt empty bowle among the thirſtie. Ignorance is an inſenſible hunger. The water of life is the best wine. He that robs mee of my invention bids himſelfe welcome to another mans table, and I will bid him welcome when he is gone. The vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious man piſſeth more then hee drinkes. That no man can drinke a health out of the cup of bleſsing. To ſurfet vpon wit is more dangerous then to want it. He that's ouercome of any
<pb facs="tcp:20960:32"/>
paſsion is dry drunke. Tis eaſier to fill the belly of faith, then the eye of reaſon. The rich glutton is better fed then taught. That faith is the elbow for a heauy ſoule to leane on. Hee that ſins that he may repent, ſurfets that he may take phyſicke. He that riſeth without thankſgiuing, goes away and payes not for his ordinarie. He that begins to repent when he is old, neuer waſhed his hands till night. That this life is but one day of three meales, or one meale of three courſes, childhood, youth, and old age. That to ſup well is to liue well, and that's the way to ſleep well. That no man goes to bed till hee dyes, nor wakes till he is dead. And therfore</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Good night to you heere &amp; good morrow hereafter. <hi>J. C.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="article">
                     <head>Nowes from the Bed.</head>
                     <p>THat the bed is the beſt rendevou of mankind, and the moſt neceſſarie ornament of a chamber. That Souldiers are good antiquaries in keeping the old faſhion, for the firſt bed was the bare ground. That a mans pillow is his beſt counſeller. That <hi>Adam</hi> lay in ſtate when the heauen was his canopie. That the naked truth is <hi>Eue,</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> lay without ſheetes. That they were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very innocent, very ignorant, or very impudent, they were not aſhamed the heauens ſhould ſee them lye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a couerlet. That it is likely <hi>Eue</hi> ſtudied Aſtronomie, which makes the poſteritie of her ſex euer ſince to lye on their backs. That the circumference of the bed is nothing ſo wide as the convex of the heauens, yet it containes a
<pb facs="tcp:20960:33"/>
whole world. That the fiue ſences are the greateſt ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. That a ſlothfull man is but a reaſonable Dormouſe. That the ſoule euer wakes to watch the body. That a Iealous man ſleeps dog-ſleep. That ſleep makes no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between a wiſe-man and a foole. That for all times ſleep is the beſt bedfellow. That the deuill and miſchiefe euer wake. That loue is a dreame. That the prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hopes of ambitious men are like pleaſing dreames, fartheſt off when awake. That the bed payes <hi>Venus</hi> more cuſtome then all the world beſide. That if dreames and wiſhes had been all true, there had not been ſince Popery one maide to make a Nun of. That the ſecure man ſleeps ſoundly and is hardly to be wak't. That the charitable man dreames of building Churches, but ſtarts to thinke the vngodly Courtier will pull them down again. That great ſleepers were neuer dangerous in a ſtate. That there is a naturall reaſon why popiſh Prieſts chuſe the bed to confeſſe their women vpon, for they hold it neceſſarie that humiliation ſhould follow ſhrift. That if the bed ſhould ſpeake all it knowes, it would put many to the bluſh. That it is fit the bed ſhould know more then paper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>R. S.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20960:33"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
